In that time frame,
early '90s or just '90s I suppose writ
large, what was it like being a woman in
the police force?
>> It was a really tough environment when I
first got there. There were a few days
in the very beginning when I was an
officer that you know, the good thing
about the officer like when I got there
the department was
85 probably percent African-American.
The city was largely 89%
African-American, so largely
African-American. Certainly very few
white females. There was very few
females. So I would think we were about
11% women on the department of 5,000,
5,200 I think when I came on.
Size of our department. So very few
women, very few white women. It's hard
to think back to '99. Sexual harassment
was
commonplace. Nobody talked about it.
Nobody cared about it. It wasn't an
issue. Like it just it it happened every
day and you just
you know, you work through it. I grew up
with two older brothers, so I kind of
knew how to navigate it a little bit,
you know, I'd listen my brothers gave me
advice how to deal with some of this.
The good thing is as an officer,
you very quickly establish yourself.
And I established myself as an officer
early on as a worker. Like I came to
work, I did my job. I don't need anybody
to do me any favors. You don't need to
look out for me. I don't need a partner.
I can ride by myself. I'm good.
Once I made sergeant though, the
harassment got worse. I mean I I had a
lieutenant that was really really
sexually harassing. I mean not just me,
but several women.
Physical harassment. I mean like getting
you in a on a midnight shift in a
sergeant's office and closing the door
and you know, putting her hands on you
and things like that. I remember saying
to my boyfriend at the time, I was like,
you know what? I got real thick skin. I
can take all kinds of comments. I don't
mind any of that stuff. But I'm not
going to let people put their hands on
me. That's just not going to happen. So
the harassment was pretty intense. It
was a it was a really tough environment.
>> So what happened?
>> I eventually
So I had a a lieutenant when I made
sergeant, and I was sent over to um
Southeast Washington. I was patrolling
in Southeast. I had really a good squad.
I worked nights, permanent nights. So, I
had a lieutenant that was harassing me
and some other women, but me pretty
intensely. Calling me on the radio,
forcing me to drive him around, putting
me in a cruiser with him, making me
drive him around.
Just not letting me do my job. Constant
harassment, calling me on the radio,
bringing me to the office, make me drive
him somewhere, things like that. So, I
finally, after several times of asking
him to leave me alone, I finally filed a
sexual harassment complaint. He had put
his hands on me several times.
So, I filed a complaint, and I remember
going down to the EEO office and filing
this complaint, and they asked me to
write a list of anybody who would ever
Well, first of all, before I went down,
my partner, one of my fellow sergeants,
who was a a black male officer, said to
me one day,
"We were out riding together." And the
lieutenant had called me in, and my
partner said to me, the other sergeant
said,
"How long are you going to let this keep
going on before you do something about
it?"
>> Mhm.
>> And I was like, "What are you talking
about?" He's like,
"I hope you're writing this stuff down.
I hope you're going to say something to
somebody because this can't go on like
this." Again, a man, not a woman,
another male police officer, basically
said to me, "If you're not going to
stand up for yourself, nobody else is
going to stand up for you." And so, when
he said that, it
clicked, and I was like, he's trying to
say either you're going to allow this to
keep happening, or you don't want it to
happen, and you do something about it.
So, I after that conversation, I filed
this complaint.
I list all the people who had witnessed
because my harasser made no no effort to
hide it. He made horrible comments and
grabbed
women in front of others all the time.
So, I listed it 17 different witnesses,
and they did the investigation, and
literally, I left the EEO office, I went
to court, I had court that day, and I
was in court 20 minutes after I left the
EEO office from filing my complaint. My
harasser, the lieutenant, texted me on
my beeper. We had beepers back then.
And said, "I know what you're doing and
you're not going to get away with this."
Like, so it was supposed to be
confidential, but within 20 minutes of
leaving the office, the person who was
doing my investigation called him and
told him that I had made a complaint.
>> Gross.
>> So, I had to go back to work in that
environment, one of the most violent
areas of Washington D.C. From that day
forward, he prohibited me from
partnering with anybody. He refused to
allow me to ride with anybody else. He
continued the harassment. He you know,
came into my office the next day, shut
the door and said, "Look, I know that
what you're doing, you need to back
down. You need to withdraw this
complaint. You're not going to win."
They sustained the complaint. So, the
investigation, all the witness I listed,
they were all men.
I didn't think any of them would tell
the truth. Nobody wanted to go against
this higher ranking person. And every
single one of them told the truth. They
all wrote down what they saw. They all
not only talked about what they saw him
doing to me, but what they saw him doing
to other women. And I was just shocked.
>> Mhm.
>> I always say to women, you don't realize
when you're in these scenarios,
decent men that observe these things
going on, they don't like it either.
Right? They don't like it either. And
and those other men that I was working
with, they didn't like it either. And
some of them, this guy had harassed
their girlfriends or their wives or you
know what I mean?
So,
that really
made an impression on me that so many of
the men that I work with stood up and
did the right thing there. So, when when
it was time for him to be disciplined
for this,
when we got to trial board,
I walk in a trial board for the
discipline to come down and they told me
they had to drop the whole case and
throw it out. And I'm like, "Why?
What happened?"
And they said, "Well, we missed the 90
days." In the District of Columbia, you
have to bring discipline within 90 days
of the day that you knew or should have
known about the misconduct. They sat on
this investigation till day 91 and then
turned it in. So, literally after all of
that, they threw the case out. And they
said, "Well, we'll just transfer you.
Where do you want to be transferred to?"
And I was like, "I don't want to be
transferred. I didn't do anything wrong.
Don't transfer me. Transfer him. I
didn't do anything." He later had
several other complaints come forward
and eventually was terminated for a
severe case with another
multiple other subordinates later on.
But I will tell you this. Now,
everything above the rank of
captain in the police department is
appointed, right? You civil service exam
for sergeant, lieutenant, and captain.
After captain,
it's appointed by the chief of police.
You're an appointed rank, and you're
also at will. So, if you can get
appointed to inspector or commander, but
you also can get demoted with no cause,
either. So, I remember one of my
mentors, another mentor, a lieutenant.
There was a captain and a lieutenant
that were both good mentors to me there.
The captain of the two mentors I had
there
pulled me aside after this complaint and
said, "You did the right thing.
He's been harassing them in here for
years, and somebody needed to stand up,
so you did the right thing." He said,
"But just know you'll never make it past
the rank of captain." Because my That
lieutenant was very well connected at
the time to the chief of police. So,
very friendly with the chief of police,
that whole administration. So, I said,
"That's fine. Like, that's fine." I
wasn't thinking, you know, long-term
longevity and promotion.
>> That actually ties into what I was going
to ask you because it strikes me as
an incredibly brave thing to do. I
imagine not everyone in your situation
would have done that. I mean, in fact,
they didn't, right? I imagine there's a
lot of fear around There could be a lot
of fear around the political or job, you
know, professional repercussions of
voicing something like that, especially
during a period when that was not
common.
>> Well, remember my driver in life, Tim.
If you think about this, and harassers
work this way.
My goal in life is to take care of my
son. I'm a single mom.
After he knew I made a complaint, he was
threatening my job. He was really making
it very difficult for me to come to
work. Like it was terrifying to come to
work, you know?
And
I was fighting for my job. I can't lose
my job. I have a son to take care of and
I'm not going to lose my job because
somebody wants to be a bully. And that's
the motivation. It was It was terrible.
I was sick to my stomach every day. I
was going in the bathroom and throwing
up. I mean, it was when I got to work
and just every time I heard his voice on
the radio, it was terrible for me. But I
also couldn't afford to lose my job. I
was not going to let somebody to force
me out of my goal. And I had a a son to
take care of, so I couldn't afford that.
I was going to fight until I
knew that I was safe.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's sort of focusing
forcing function, right? I mean, having
that singular priority. So, it seems
like I mean, the predictions about you
never rising above the rank of what was
it, captain?
>> Captain.
>> Seems like that fellow wasn't exactly
the the Nostradamus of of predicting the
future.
>> [laughter]
>> Could you walk us through sort of how
things
progressed and why were you able
to continue to excel? Did his prediction
just turn out to be completely false?
>> I think it would have been accurate. I I
tell you what, it the stars aligned for
me. So, I took sergeant test at 3 years.
I was eligible for lieutenant at 5. I
took the lieutenant's test at 5 years. I
came in number one on that test. I took
the captain's test 7 years. I came in
number three on that test. So, I got
promoted bang bang bang 3 years, 5
years, 7 years. I was a captain at 7
years.
I would have never gone past the rank of
captain in that current administration.
And then Marion Barry gets arrested, our
mayor.
>> Mhm.
>> Marion Barry is taken out and replaced
by the control board.
The control board comes in 1998. I'm a
captain at the time.
Marion Barry is now taken out of play.
The control board takes over. They bring
in Chuck Ramsey, an outsider who knows
nobody
>> Mhm.
>> in the department. He doesn't know
anybody. He's got no click. He's got no
boys.
>> Mhm.
>> Everybody's fresh. So, he comes in as
I'm lieutenant just making captain,
takes over the police department as a
complete outsider, and is doing his
assessment of what officials what
command level officials he wanted to
have on his team, and he appointed me
from the rank of captain to be an
inspector to take over major narcotics
branch with less than 8 years on the
job.
I was 29, I think.